Contact

Department of Biostatistics and Computational Biology

Information Dana-Farber Cancer Institute

twitter: @stephaniehicks 450 Brookline Avenue email: shicks@jimmy.harvard.edu Boston, MA 02215 USA website: stephaniehicks.com

RESEARCH Interests

My research interests are focused on developing statistical methods, tools and software for the analysis of genomics data. Specifically, my research addresses statistical challenges in epigenomics and functional genomics such as the pre-processing, normalization, analysis of raw high-throughput data (microarray and next-generation sequencing) leading to an improved quantification and understanding of biological variability.

Current Appointment Postdoctoral Research Fellow, Boston MA

2013 - Present

Department of Biostatistics and Computational Biology, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute

Department of Biostatistics, Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health

Mentor: Rafael Irizarry

EDUCATION

2013 PhD., Statistics, Rice University, Houston, TX USA

Doctoral Advisors: Marek Kimmel, Ph.D. (Rice, Statistics) and

Sharon Plon, M.D., Ph.D. (Baylor College of Medicine)

Dissertation: Probabilistic Models for Genetic and Genomic Data with Missing Information

M.A., Statistics, Rice University, Houston, TX USA 2012

2007 B.S., Mathematics, Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, LA USA magna cum laude, Phi Beta Kappa

Professional EXPERIENCE

08/2013 -Postdoctoral Research Fellow, DFCI and HSPH, Boston, MA

Mentor: Rafael Irizarry

06/2013Research Staff, Rice University, Houston, TX

2007 - 2013 Graduate Student Researcher, Rice University, Houston, TX

Advisors: Marek Kimmel and Sharon Plon (Baylor College of Medicine)

2006 Undergraduate Researcher (REU), Statistics, University of Wisconsin, Madison, WI

Mentors: Murray Clayton and Jo Handelsman

2005 Undergraduate Researcher (REU), Statistics, Rice University, Houston, TX

Mentor: Javier Rojo

2005 - 2007Undergraduate Researcher, Psychology, LSU, Baton Rouge, LA

Mentor: Robert Mathews

2005 - 2007Undergraduate Tutor, Roadmap 2 Redesign Program, LSU, Baton Rouge, LA

Tutored college algebra, trigonometry and pre-calculus students.

Undergraduate Tutor, LSU, Baton Rouge, LA 2003 - 2004

Tutored students at Scotlandville Magnet High School in algebra for 3hrs/week.

Research **Pre-prints**

[1] Hicks SC, Teng M, Irizarry RA. (2015). On the widespread and critical impact of systematic bias and batch effects in single-cell RNA-Seq data. bioRxiv. doi: http://dx.doi.org/10. 1101/025528.

Peer-reviewed Journal Articles

- [1] J Saliba, R Zabriskie, R Ghosh, BC Powell, **S Hicks**, M Kimmel, Q Meng, DI Ritter, DA Wheeler, RA Gibbs, FTF Tsai, SE Plon. Pharmacogenetic characterization of naturally occurring germline NT5C1A variants to chemotherapeutic nucleoside analogs. *Pharmacogenetics and Genomics* 2016, In press. PMID: 26906009.
- [2] **Hicks SC**¹, Irizarry RA. (2015). quantro: a data-driven approach to guide the choice of an appropriate normalization method. *Genome Biol* **16**:117. PMID: 26040460.
- [3] Osman AA, Neskey DM, Katsonis P, Patel AA, Ward AM, Hsu TK, Hicks SC, McDonald TO, Ow TJ, Alves MO, Pickering CR, Skinner HD, Zhao M, Sturgis EM, Kies MS, El-Naggar A, Perrone F, Licitra L, Bossi P, Kimmel M, Frederick MJ, Lichtarge O, Myers JN. (2015). Evolutionary Action Score of TP53 Coding Variants Is Predictive of Platinum Response in Head and Neck Cancer Patients. Cancer Res 75: 1-11. PMID: 25691460
- [4] Neskey DM, Osman AA, Ow TJ, Katsonis P, McDonald T, Hicks SC, Hsu TK, Pickering CR, Ward A, Patel A, Yordy JS, Skinner HD, Giri U, Sano D, Story MD, Beadle BM, El-Naggar AK, Kies MS, William WN, Caulin C, Frederick M, Kimmel M, Myers JN, Lichtarge O. (2015). Evolutionary Action score of TP53 (EAp53) identifies high risk mutations associated with decreased survival and increased distant metastases in head and neck cancer. Cancer Res 75: 1527-1536. PMID: 25634208.
- [5] Berger RL, Li LT, Hicks SC, Liang MK. (2014). Suture versus preperitoneal polypropylene mesh for elective umbilical hernia repairs. J Surg Res 192: 426-431. PMID: 24980854
- [6] Brahmbhatt R, Carter SA, Hicks SC, Berger DH, Liang MK. (2014). Identifying Risk Factors for Surgical Site Complications after Laparoscopic Ventral Hernia Repair: Evaluation of the Ventral Hernia Working Group Grading System. Surg Infect (Larchmt) 15: 187-193. PMID: 24773169
- [7] Carter SA, Hicks SC, Brahmbhatt R, Liang MK. (2014). Recurrence and Pseudorecurrence after Laparoscopic Ventral Hernia Repair: Predictors and Patient-focused Outcomes. Am Surg 80: 138-148. PMID: 24480213
- [8] Hicks SC. (2014). When Women in Statistics Come to Know Their Power. Chance 27.
- [9] Li LT, Hicks SC, Davila JA, Kao LS, Berger RL, Arita NA, Liang MK. (2014). Circular Closure is Associated with the Lowest Rate of Surgical Site Infection Following Stoma Reversal: A Systematic Review and Multiple Treatment Meta-analysis. Colorectal Dis 16: 406-416. PMID: 24422861
- [10] Li LT, Brahmbhatt R, Hicks SC, Davila JA, Berger DH, Liang MK. (2014). Prevalence of Surgical Site Infection at the Stoma Site following Four Skin Closure Techniques: A Retrospective Cohort Study. Dig Surg 31: 73-78. PMID: 24776653
- [11] Li LT, Jafrani RJ, Becker NS, Berger RL, Hicks SC, Davila JA, Liang MK. (2014). Outcomes of acute versus elective primary ventral hernia repair. J Trauma Acute Care Surg 76: 523-528. PMID: 24458061
- [12] Liang MK, Li LT, Nguyen MT, Berger RL, Hicks SC, Kao LS. (2014). Abdominal reoperation and mesh explantation following open ventral hernia repair with mesh. Am J Surg 204: 670-676. PMID: 25241955.
- [13] Liang MK, Berger RL, Nguyen MT, Hicks SC, Li LT, Leong M. (2014). Outcomes with Porcine Acellular Dermal Matrix versus Synthetic Mesh and Suture in Complicated Open Ventral Hernia Repair. Surg Infect 15: 506-512. PMID: 25215466.
- [14] Nguyen MT, Berger RL, Hicks SC, Davila JA, Li LT, Kao LS, Liang MK. (2014). Comparison of Outcomes of Synthetic Mesh vs Suture Repair of Elective Primary Ventral Herniorrhaphy: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis. JAMA Surg 31: 73-78. PMID: 24554114

¹ 'Highly Accessed' on BioMed Central

- [15] Nguyen MT, Phatak UR, Li LT, Hicks SC, Moffett JM, Arita NA, Berger RL, Kao LS, Liang MK. (2014). Review of stoma site and midline incisional hernias after stoma reversal. J Surg Res 190: 504-509. PMID: 24560428
- [16] Berger RL, Li LT, Hicks SC, Davila JA, Kao LS, Liang MK. (2013). Development and validation of a risk-stratification score for surgical site occurrence and surgical site infection after open ventral hernia repair. J Am Coll Surg. 217: 974-982. PMID: 24051068
- [17] Clapp ML, Hicks SC, Awad SS, Liang MK. (2013). Trans-cutaneous Closure of Central Defects (TCCD) in Laparoscopic Ventral Hernia Repairs (LVHR). World J Surg. 37: 42-51. PMID: 23052806.
- [18] Liang MK, Clapp M, Li LT, Berger RL, Hicks SC, Awad S. (2013). Patient Satisfaction, Chronic Pain, and Functional Status following Laparoscopic Ventral Hernia Repair. World J Surg. 37: 530-537. PMID: 23212794.
- [19] Liang MK, Li LT, Avellaneda A, Moffett JM, Hicks SC, Awad SS. (2013). Outcomes and Predictors of Incisional Surgical Site Infection in Stoma Reversal. JAMA Surg 148: 183-189. PMID: 23426597.
- [20] Liang MK, Berger RL, Li LT, Davila JA, **Hicks SC**, Kao LS. (2013). Outcomes of laparoscopic vs open repair of primary ventral hernias. *JAMA Surg* **148**: 1043-1048. PMID: 24005537
- [21] Neskey DM, Klein JD, Hicks S, Garden AS, Bell DM, El-Naggar Ak, Kies MS, Weber RS, Kupferman ME. (2013). Prognostic Factors Associated With Decreased Survival in Patients With Acinic Cell Carcinoma. JAMA Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 139: 1195-1202. PMID: 24076756
- [22] Nguyen MT, Li LT, Hicks SC, Davila JA, Suliburk JW, Leong M, Kao LS, Berger DH, Liang MK. (2013). Readmission following open ventral hernia repair: incidence, indications, and predictors. Am J Surg 206: 942-948. PMID: 24296099
- [23] Subramanian A, Clapp ML, **Hicks SC**, Awad SS, Liang MK. (2013). Laparoscopic ventral hernia repair: Primary versus secondary hernias. *J Surg Res* **181**: e1-5. PMID: 22795342.
- [24] Hicks S, Plon SE, Kimmel M. (2013). Statistical Analysis of Missense Mutation Classifiers. Hum Mut 34: 405-406. PMID: 23086893.
- [25] Cheung HC², San Lucas FA, Hicks S, Chang K, Bertuch AA, Ribes-Zamora A. (2012). An S/T-Q cluster domain census unveils new putative targets under Tel1/Mec1 control. BMC Genomics 13: 664. PMID: 23176708.
- [26] Hicks S³, Wheeler DE, Plon SE, Kimmel M. (2011). Prediction of Missense Mutation Functionality Depends on both the Algorithm and Sequence Alignment Employed. *Hum Mut.* 32: 661-668. PMID: 21480434.

Invited Talks

- [1] Introduction to R and R Package Demonstration. Dept of Biostatistics and Computational Biology Training Sessions. Dana-Farber Cancer Institute. 2016 March 9. Boston, MA.
- [2] Why Statistics Matters in the Analysis of Genomics Data. Computational Biology Seminar, Department of Biology, Louisiana State University. 2015 Feb 11. Baton Rouge, LA.
- [3] Normalization of DNA methylation and Gene Expression Data in the Context of Global Variation. Bioinformatics Meeting, Division of Immunology, Harvard Medical School. 2014 Sept 18. Boston, MA.

Contributed Talks

² 'Highly Accessed' on BioMed Central

³Cited and Discussed in Nature **482**: 257-262. 09 Feb 2012. PMID: 22318607

- [1] **Hicks S**⁴, Teng M, Irizarry R. On the widespread and critical impact of batch effects and systematic bias in single-cell RNA-Seq data. 2015 PQG Conference: Single-cell Genomics: Technology, Analysis, and Applications. 2015 Nov 5-6. Boston, MA.
- [2] **Hicks SC**, Irizarry R. quantro: When should you use quantile normalization? Flashlight talk at *Bioconductor Conference*. 2014 Jul 30-Aug 1. Boston, MA.
- [3] **Hicks S**, Plon SE, Kimmel M. Modeling Discovery Of Functional SNPs From Genome Scale Data. *Joint Statistical Meetings*. 2011 Aug 5. Miami, FL.
- [4] **Hicks S**, Plon SE, Wheeler DE, Kimmel M. Prediction of Missense Mutation Functionality Depends on both the Algorithm and Sequence Alignment Employed. *Human Genome Variation Society's Exploring the Functional Consequences of Genomic Variation Meeting*. 2010 Nov 1. Washington, D.C.

Conference Proceedings

- [1] Saliba J, Trevino LR, Meng Q, Zabriskie R, Powell B, **Hicks S**, Kimmel M, Cheung H, Muzny DM, Reid JG, Wheeler D, Gibbs RA, and Plon SE. Abstract 5113: Functional analysis of genomic variants identified through whole exome sequencing for susceptibility to lymphocytic leukemia. *AACR 103rd Annual Meeting.* 2012 Mar 31-Apr 4. Chicago, IL.
- [2] Saliba J, Zabriskie R, Powell B, Hicks S, Kimmel M, Cheung H, Ritter D, Muzny DM, Reid JG, Wheeler DA, Gibbs RA, Plon SE. Abstract A8: Functional analysis of genomic variants identified through whole exome sequencing of pediatric lymphocytic leukemia kindreds. AACR Special Conference: Pediatric Cancer at the Crossroads: Translating Discovery into Improved Outcomes. 2013 Nov 3-6. San Diego, CA.

Selected Poster Presentations

- [1] **Hicks S**, Teng M, Irizarry R. On the widespread and critical impact of batch effects and systematic bias in single-cell RNA-Seq data. Poster presented at 2015 Genome Informatics. 2015 Oct 28-31. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratories.
- [2] **Hicks S**, Irizarry R. When to use Quantile Normalization? Poster presented at: 2014 Women in Statistics Conference. 2014 May 15-17. Cary, NC.
- [3] **Hicks S**, Irizarry R. Estimating cell composition of whole blood using differentially methylated regions. Poster presented at: 2013 PQG Conference. 2013. Nov 14-15. Boston, MA.
- [4] **Hicks S**, Plon SE, Kimmel M. postMUT: A Statistical Tool for Combining Predictions of Missense Mutation Functionality using Capture-Recapture Methods. Poster presented at: 63nd Annual Meeting of The American Society of Human Genetics. 2013. Oct 22-26. Boston, MA.
- [5] Kimmel M, **Hicks S**, Plon SE. Applications of Hidden Markov Models with Conditional Emission Probabilities to Identify Regions of Identity-By-Descent in Whole-Exome Sequencing Data. Poster presented at: 63nd Annual Meeting of The American Society of Human Genetics. 2013. Oct 22-26. Boston, MA.
- [6] **Hicks S**, Plon SE, Kimmel M. Capture-Recapture Models for Evaluation of Algorithms Estimating Functionality of Missense Mutations. Poster presented at: 62nd Annual Meeting of The American Society of Human Genetics. 2012 Nov 6-12. San Francisco, CA.
- [7] **Hicks S**, Plon SE, Kimmel M. Bernoulli mixture models in application of the evaluation of algorithms estimating functionality of missense mutations. Poster presented at: *Beyond The Genome*. 2012 Sept 27-29. Boston, MA.
- [8] **Hicks S**, Plon SE, Kimmel M. Bernoulli Mixture Models in Application of the Evaulation of Algorithms Estimating Functionality of Missense Mutations. Poster presented at: *International Conference in Stochastic Processes*. 2012. Aug 21-25. Houston, TX.

⁴Selected for a Stellar Abstract Award

- [9] Hicks S, Plon SE, Kimmel M. Using a Second-order Hidden Markov Model to Identify Regions of Identity-By-Descent in Exome Sequencing Data. Poster presented at: 12th International Congress of Human Genetics/61st Annual Meeting of The American Society of Human Genetics. 2011 Nov 12-15. Montreal, Canada.
- [10] Hicks S, Plon SE, Wheeler DE, Kimmel, M. Prediction of Missense Mutation Functionality Depends on both the Algorithm and Sequence Alignment Employed. Poster presented at: 60th Annual Meeting of the American Society of Human Genetics. 2010 Nov 2-6. Washington, D.C.
- [11] **Hicks S**, Plon SE, Wheeler DE, Kimmel, M. Prediction of Missense Mutation Functionality Depends on both the Algorithm and Sequence Alignment Employed. Poster presented at: 4th Annual Meeting of the Genomics of Common Diseases. 2010 Oct 6-9. Houston, TX.
- [12] Cheung HC, San Lucas F, **Hicks S**, Chang K, Plon SE, Bertuch AA, Ribes-Zamora A. S/T-Q Cluster Domains in Saccharomyces cerevisiae: a bioinformatic census and analysis. Poster presented at: *BioScience Research Collaborative Grand Opening*. 2010 Apr 1. Houston, TX.
- [13] **Hicks S**, Plon SE, Wheeler DE, Kimmel, M. Predicting Functionality of Missense Mutations with Varying Levels of Evolutionary Depth. Poster presented at: *Computational & Theoretical Biology Symposium*. 2009 Dec 4-6. Houston, TX.
- [14] **Hicks S**, Plon SE, Wheeler DE, Kimmel, M. Predicting Functionality of Missense Mutations with Varying Levels of Evolutionary Depth. Poster presented at: 59th Annual Meeting of the American Society of Human Genetics. 2009 Oct 20-24. Honolulu, HI.

Ph.D. Dissertation

[1] **Hicks SC**. Probabilistic Models for Genetic and Genomic Data with Missing Information, Ph.D. Thesis, Rice University, 2013.

SOFTWARE Bioconductor and Github

- [1] explainr: An R-package to translate S3 objects into text using standard templates in a simple and convenient way. Developed at ROpenSci Unconference with Hilary Parker, David Robinson and Roger Peng. [Available on GitHub]
- [2] quantro: An R-package that can be used to test for differences between groups of distributions to guide the choice if quantile normalization should be used [Available on Bioconductor]
- [3] quantroSim: A supporting data simulation R-package for the quantro R-package to simulate gene expression and DNA methylation data [Available on GitHub]
- [4] postMUT: A tool implemented in Perl and R to predict the functionality of missense mutations [Available on GitHub]

COMMUNITY CODING EXPERIENCE

- Sept 2015 Mozilla Open Science Leadership Summit (website), Mozilla, Toronto, Canada Invited to work with community leaders furthering open practice and open science through creating community events, tools for collaboration and learning resources.
- Mar 2015 **ROpenSci Unconference** (website), GitHub, San Francisco, CA Invited to work with over 40 R enthusiasts from industry, academia, non-profits and government on projects supporting open data, open science and data visualization in R.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE	2016	Co-instructor, Introduction to Data Science (HSPH - BIO 260) Co-taught lectures with Rafael Irizarry, developed course material
	2015	Teaching Assistant , Statistical Methods for Functional Genomics (CSHL) Contributed course material, gave a lecture, answered questions.
	2015	Contributor and Discussion Leader (1) Statistics and R for the Life Sciences (Harvard edX - PH525.1x) (2) Case study: DNA methylation data analysis (Harvard edX - PH525.8x) Contributed course material, created screencasts, developed assessments, answered questions. Courses taught by Rafael Irizarry with Teaching Assistant Mike Love.
	2014	Lead Teaching Fellow, Data Science (Harvard - CS109) Held weekly lab sections. Developed course material, homework and solutions. Coordinated and directed 25 teaching fellows. All material available on: Github Course taught by Rafael Irizarry and Verena Kaynig-Fittkau.
	2014	Discussion Leader , Data Analysis for Genomics (Harvard edX - PH525x) Course taught by Rafael Irizarry with Teaching Assistant Mike Love.
	2010, 2011	Teaching Assistant , Probability in Bioinformatics and Genetics (Rice - STAT 423/623) Grade homeworks, provide solutions, hold office hours and gave several guest lectures.
	2010	Teaching Assistant , Applied Stochastic Processes (Rice - STAT 552) Grade homeworks, provide solutions, hold office hours and gave several guest lectures.
	2008, 2009	Lab Instructor , Introduction to Statistics for the Biosciences (Rice - STAT 305) Hold labs 3hr/week to teach students to use R.
	2007, 2008	Teaching Assistant , Probability and Statistics (Rice - STAT 310) Grade homeworks, provide solutions, hold office hours and gave several guest lectures.
Grants and Awards	2015 2015 2014 2011 2008 - 2011 2007 2007 2005 - 2007 2004 - 2005 2003 - 2007	Stellar Abstract Award for the 2015 PQG Conference Travel award for the Genome Informatics Meeting 2015 at CSHL Travel award for the Women in Statistics Conference 2014 Travel and tuition award for the 16th Annual Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics at University of Washington (Population Genetics, Coalescent Theory modules) NIH T32 Training Grant Fellow, Rice University Inducted into Phi Beta Kappa LSU Austin Chapter Scholarship Award LA-STEM Research Scholars, LSU HMMI Professors Program, LSU TOPS Tuition Award, LSU
TECHNICAL SKILLS	Programming: R, Python, Git, Perl, LaTeX, SAS, Matlab, Shell scripting Operating Systems: Mac OS X, Unix, Windows	
Journal Referee / Reviewer	$Bioinformatics,\ Biometrics,\ BMC\ Medical\ Genetics,\ Genome\ Biology,\ Human\ Mutation,\ PLoS\ Computational\ Biology$	
Professional Memberships	Member, American Statistical Association (ASA) Member, American Mathematical Society (AMS) Member, American Society of Human Genetics (ASHG)	